Comrades!
The great Soviet Union has conquered the Volga, the longest river in all of Europe!
Huge dams power our great leap forward!
The grand canals connecting five seas are symbols of the people's unity!
Bring the Mother River's gift to all!
This is the true victory of Socialism!
The great Soviet Union is no more.
But its legacy still remains today.
Check that legacy on Google Maps.
Volgograd. Site of the bloodiest battle in WWII.
Defended by brave citizens, it's now a thriving metropolis home to a million people.
Wait... what's this?
There's a strange white structure along the riverbank.
It's apparently called the "Beloye Morye."
In Russian, that means "The White Sea."
The White Sea?!
White doesn't suit Russia!
Russia must be dyed a beautiful red!
This "White Sea" is actually a highly toxic pool.
When chemical weapons factories were built in the Soviet era,
their waste products were dumped right here.
Mercury, phenol, benzopyrene
Massive amounts of these toxins are stored in a reservoir right next to the Volga River.
And it's right near residential areas.
Since the 70s, they've dumped lime to neutralize the waste, which is why it turned white.
The Volga, Russia's "Mother River," is now facing a severe environmental crisis.
Today, let's explore development and conservation through the environmental issues of the Volga.
The Volga River is 3,530 km long, with a basin area of 1.36 million square kilometers.
It's Europe's longest river, with a basin roughly 3.6 times the size of Japan.
About 60 million people live in this basin—that's 40% of Russia's population.
Most major Russian cities rely on the blessings of this river.
It's especially vital for Moscow's drinking water.
90% of Moscow's water comes from the Volga.
The basin also supports over 25% of Russia's total agricultural production.
Russians call it "Volga-Matushka," or "Mother Volga."
So, what happened to this Mother River?
The cause lies in the massive development projects of the Soviet era.
In the early 1900s, the USSR industrialized rapidly.
They needed electricity and waterways to transport goods.
So, the Soviets decided to artificially "remodel" the Volga River.
The results were indeed remarkable.
Eight massive dams were built, generating huge amounts of power.
A network of canals connected the Baltic, Black, White, Azov, and Caspian seas.
Moscow became known as the "Port of the Five Seas."
But this rapid development came at a terrible price.
Many forced laborers were used to build these dams and canals.
Thousands are believed to have died building the Moscow Canal, finished in 1937.
Furthermore, massive reservoirs were created behind the dams.
The largest is about seven times the size of Lake Biwa.
Many villages were submerged to make way for these giant lakes.
Residents were forcibly relocated, and their displacement left homes at the bottom of the lake.
Church steeples still poke through the surface, reminding us of what was lost.
Even worse is the change in the river's flow.
Dams have greatly reduced the Volga's water flow.
Some reports say it's down to just one-tenth of its original flow.
When a river slows down, what happens?
Pollutants don't wash away; they just settle in place.
Industrial waste, fertilizers, and pesticides from farms...
These built up at the bottom of reservoirs as meters of toxic sludge.
The Soviet Union prioritized immediate results.
Power, shipping, irrigation.
There were huge short-term benefits.
But the Volga is now suffering the cost of those short-term gains.
The Volga is now one of the most polluted rivers in Russia.
40% of all Russian wastewater is concentrated in this one river.
Soviet-era environmental laws existed.
But for factories, it was cheaper to pay the fines than to clean their waste.
This practice didn't change after the Soviet collapse.
Even now, only 10% of wastewater treatment meets regulatory standards.
It's been 30 years since the USSR fell, and 90 since the first dams.
Yet there's been no real improvement in water quality.
The government launched a massive 205 billion ruble cleanup project,
investing about 400 billion yen over six years to save the Volga.
However, the Accounts Chamber has noted that there's almost no visible progress.
The reason: "time bombs" buried in the Soviet era are everywhere.
The "White Sea" I mentioned earlier is a perfect example.
This 28-hectare white structure in Volgograd...
...houses between 1.5 and 3.5 million tons of toxic waste.
During the Cold War's arms race with the United States,
the USSR built chemical weapons and dumped the waste into this pool.
Toxins thousands of times above safety levels still lie dormant there.
In the 70s, after dumping massive amounts of lime for neutralization,
the pond turned white, earning the name "White Sea."
Under the Soviets, this factory was a military secret.
Pointing out pollution was considered an act of treason.
Criticism simply wasn't allowed.
When the USSR collapsed, no one wanted to take responsibility.
In a crisis, there was no budget for the environment.
The treatment costs are astronomical.
So, the problem just kept getting pushed aside.
It's now covered by a white dome as a temporary containment measure,
but snowmelt or heavy rain could leak toxins into the Volga at any time.
There are many of these toxic bombs hidden along the Volga basin.
In the era of developmental dictatorship, only results mattered.
Costs were hidden, criticism silenced, and duty made vague.
The result is this "White Sea."
Sadly, the day we see Mother Volga restored to its true beauty may still be far off.
Even so, I hope we can move forward one step at a time.
The Volga supports 60 million lives as Russia's Mother River.
But through Soviet obsession with short-term growth,
the price was hidden, leaving a dark legacy that persists today.
Even 90 years later, the Mother River is still in pain.
How do we balance development and the environment?
I made this video because I believe this is a vital question for every country and every era.
See you in the next video. Have a good day!